<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://richardvesely.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://richardvesely.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2024-03-09T21:35:22+01:00</updated><id>https://richardvesely.com/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Richard Veselý</title><subtitle>Write an awesome description for your new site here. You can edit this line in _config.yml. It will appear in your document head meta (for Google search results) and in your feed.xml site description.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">The 1000-published-words-a-day experiment</title><link href="https://richardvesely.com/letters/2024/02/16/The-1000-words-a-day-experiment.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The 1000-published-words-a-day experiment" /><published>2024-02-16T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2024-02-16T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://richardvesely.com/letters/2024/02/16/The%201000%20words%20a%20day%20experiment</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://richardvesely.com/letters/2024/02/16/The-1000-words-a-day-experiment.html"><![CDATA[<p>Lately I have often felt a need to write about something that interests me while I was away from keyboard. However, when I sit down to write I feel a block. I am not sure why that is but I suspect that it has to do something not wanting to publish imperfect things. Or just being afraid I won’t be able to formulate my thoughts. As if either of those points mattered. Hence I just want to try to publish 1000 words a day regardless of quality for a week.</p>

<p>Why am I doing this?</p>
<ol>
  <li>To see how it will make me feel.</li>
  <li>To understand whether I am not writing more (despite often feeling like I want to) because I am afraid or because I actually don’t enjoy it.</li>
  <li>To get more comfortable with putting online stuff that is probably useless to others just for my pleasure.</li>
</ol>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="letters" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Lately I have often felt a need to write about something that interests me while I was away from keyboard. However, when I sit down to write I feel a block. I am not sure why that is but I suspect that it has to do something not wanting to publish imperfect things. Or just being afraid I won’t be able to formulate my thoughts. As if either of those points mattered. Hence I just want to try to publish 1000 words a day regardless of quality for a week.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">How to behave acceptably without surpressing emotions?</title><link href="https://richardvesely.com/letters/2024/02/10/How-to-behave-acceptably-without-surpressing-emotions.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How to behave acceptably without surpressing emotions?" /><published>2024-02-10T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2024-02-10T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://richardvesely.com/letters/2024/02/10/How%20to%20behave%20acceptably%20without%20surpressing%20emotions</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://richardvesely.com/letters/2024/02/10/How-to-behave-acceptably-without-surpressing-emotions.html"><![CDATA[<p>Dear reader,<br />
I want to share with you an important realization I got today. Which is then often, when I get angry or upset I suppress the emotion so that I am not nasty to other people. But I don’t want to suppress my emotions. I don’t think it is healthy and for sure it is hindering me in my personal growth. However, when I focus on not suppressing the emotion I am nasty to other people. Which is something I don’t want to do.<br />
So what do I do?<br />
<strong>I want to learn how to feel angry (and feel it really intensely) while not being super nasty to other people.</strong>  That would be cool and useful.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="letters" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Dear reader, I want to share with you an important realization I got today. Which is then often, when I get angry or upset I suppress the emotion so that I am not nasty to other people. But I don’t want to suppress my emotions. I don’t think it is healthy and for sure it is hindering me in my personal growth. However, when I focus on not suppressing the emotion I am nasty to other people. Which is something I don’t want to do. So what do I do? I want to learn how to feel angry (and feel it really intensely) while not being super nasty to other people. That would be cool and useful.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">My main purpose in teaching science</title><link href="https://richardvesely.com/education/my-main-purpose-in-teaching-science/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="My main purpose in teaching science" /><published>2024-02-02T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2024-02-02T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://richardvesely.com/education/main-purpose-of-teaching%20copy</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://richardvesely.com/education/my-main-purpose-in-teaching-science/"><![CDATA[<p>Next year I am going to teach science to high school students and right now this thought thrills me more than anything else in my life because I articulated why I really want to do it.</p>

<p><strong>I want to make students feel confident and love themselves by giving them something that excites them and showing them that THEY can be good at it. I almost don’t care about the science.</strong></p>

<p>Here is what it means to me. In summer 2022 I have been teaching at Czech Chemistry Olympiad Camp, Běstvina and there was a student I distinctly remember (and I realised why I remember her in particular just now). When I was teaching organic chemistry, I noticed that she wasn’t attempting the problems I was setting during the lecture. From her expression I guessed this was because she was certain that she can’t solve these problems. So at some point, to prove her wrong I asked her to come to the whiteboard and solve it. She seemed very unhappy about that because was certain she wouldn’t be able to solve it. I didn’t give her any hints, or tell her any new information, I only asked few questions and she was able to solve it. I made sure to emphasise that I didn’t tell her anything new; she knew enough to solve it herself. And that’s when her approach changed. She started solving all the problems and was more engaged. She even went to all of the optional advanced lectures for this.</p>

<p>To me that was the most amazing thing I have done at the camp. I couldn’t care less whether someone knows what is the product of a hydrobromination of butadiene. But I can’t care more if someone thinks “This is hard, I can’t solve this, only the other, smarter students can do this” vs. “this is a really interesting question, how can I answer it”. Making someone realize that they can do it, that there is no “the other smarter students” is what completely moves me.</p>

<p>This resonates with me so much because it is my story. I distinctly remember looking at the Czech ChO website, seeing a photo of the team that represented Czechia at the International Chemistry Olympiad and thinking/feeling “these are completely different people than me. I’ll be glad if I ever got to the top 3 in Prague”). Well, I got three silver medals from the international chemistry Olympiad. And that wouldn’t have happened without the people who presented presented chemistry in such a way that made me realise I can learn anything if I want to. My mentors made me believe in me. Learning some cool chemistry was a nice side effect, but believing in me made changed my life completely. When I think about how lucky I am for coming across these people I just start crying from gratitude.</p>

<p>I think that unfortunately many people doubt themselves, they don’t like themselves and feel like a failure. I certainly did (and do on the worse days). And I think that potentially a first good step to solution (apart from getting therapy) is finding something you love and are good at. And I hope to help people with that by 1) showing them how amazing science is, so that they love it and 2) teaching it in so accessible way that it is clear beyond doubt that they can understand it.</p>

<p>(just a fun question to think about: “is the school system making students believe in them?”)</p>

<p>Fuck, realising how much excited I am by this I am seriously considering dropping school and starting this full time now. I am curious if I feel the same way tomorrow, before I have cup of coffee, though.</p>

<p>P.S. I think science is amazing, I also want to teach it so that I can share the beautiful “aha moments” that feel better than orgasm. But that doesn’t compare to making people believe in them.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="education" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Next year I am going to teach science to high school students and right now this thought thrills me more than anything else in my life because I articulated why I really want to do it.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">How to catch a cheater with math (math &amp;amp; coding exercise)</title><link href="https://richardvesely.com/science/2023/05/15/catch-cheater.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How to catch a cheater with math (math &amp;amp; coding exercise)" /><published>2023-05-15T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2023-05-15T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://richardvesely.com/science/2023/05/15/catch-cheater</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://richardvesely.com/science/2023/05/15/catch-cheater.html"><![CDATA[<p>This problem is inspired by a game from the <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=XTcP4oo4JI4&amp;t=33s">Primer YouTube channel</a>.</p>

<p>Your goal is to come up with an algorithm that gives you the highest score in a <a href="https://primerlearning.org/">simple game that you can find here</a>. You achieve this by correctly labeling blobs as fair or cheating.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/post_related/Thumbnail-257x300.webp" alt="primer game screenshot" /></p>

<p>Game rules:</p>

<p>At each turn, you have three options:</p>

<ol>
  <li>tell the blob to flip a coin</li>
  <li>label it as fair</li>
  <li>label it as cheater.</li>
</ol>

<p>You start with 100 coin flips, and each time you flip a coin, you must “pay” one flip.</p>

<p>If you classify the blob correctly, your score increases by one, and you receive 15 bonus flips.</p>

<p>If you classify the blob incorrectly, your score does not change, but you lose 30 flips.</p>

<p>Important information:</p>

<ol>
  <li>The occurrence of fair and fraudulent blobs is 1:1</li>
  <li>The probability that a fair blob will flip heads is 50%</li>
  <li>The probability that a fraudulent blob will flip heads is 75%</li>
</ol>

<p>Exercise:</p>

<p>In <a href="https://colab.research.google.com/drive/1BUIvHzubbpCzlsY1f0T0sWSJ2s95QAHH?usp=sharing">the interactive notebook, which you can find here</a>, you can implement an algorithm to decide what to do at each turn and test how well this algorithm works.</p>

<p>I hope that no previous programming experience is required for this, and everything is sufficiently explained in the notebook. If not, let me know in the comments.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="science" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This problem is inspired by a game from the Primer YouTube channel.]]></summary></entry></feed>